Finding Aid for Thomas W. Barwin papers, 1999-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas W. Barwin papers 1999-2006
Barwin, Thomas W.
06106 Aa 2 Ac
City Manager of Ferndale, Michigan. The collection documents issues of urban sprawl, transit planning, and smart growth in the cities of Ferndale and Detroit. The papers also concern the debate over the proposed demolition of the 8 Mile and Woodward Avenue overpass.
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by the City of Ferndale (donor no. 9769 ) in August 2006.
The collection is open to research.
Tom Barwin, as city manager of Ferndale, Michigan from 1998 to 2006, was involved in many developments relating to regional growth, transit issues, and community planning. Through his work, Barwin was credited with the economic and social revitalization of Ferndale.
While city manager, Barwin was involved in two large debates over transportation planning and administration. In 2003, MOSES (Metropolitan Organizing Strategy Enabling Strength), a group of activists sued the Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG), maintaining that their voting structure was unfair as it allowed richer communities to receive more money for transportation and city improvements. The lawsuit was later dismissed.
The 8 Mile and Woodward Avenue overpass, a bridge linking Detroit and Ferndale, was another significant debate. In 2003, the Michigan Department of Transportation conducted a series of studies on the deteriorating bridge, ultimately deciding to rebuild the bridge. Many citizens and officials, including Barwin, wanted to tear the bridge down, maintaining that the bridge was not only unattractive but acted as more of a divider between Ferndale and Detroit than a link. Advocates of rebuilding the bridge argued that rebuilding the overpass would not only be cheaper but would also provide a safer and more efficient traffic flow.
The Thomas W. Barwin papers document issues of urban sprawl, transit planning, and smart growth in the cities of Ferndale and Detroit. The papers also concern the debate over the proposed demolition of the 8 Mile and Woodward Avenue overpass. The collection consists of two series: Topical Files and 8 Mile and Woodward Overpass.
Subjects:
Barwin, Thomas W.; Ferndale (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Regional planning--Michigan, Southeastern.; Transportation--Michigan, Southeastern--Planning.; Southeast Michigan Council of Governments.; Michigan. Dept. of Transportation.; Roads--Michigan--Ferndale--Interchanges and intersections.; Roads--Michigan--Detroit--Interchanges and intersections.
Contributors:
Michigan. Dept. of Transportation.; Southeast Michigan Council of Governments.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical Files 1999-2006
  The Topical Files (1.5 linear ft., 1999-2006) consist of Barwin's files on various topics and projects and debates he was involved with while city manager. Included are Barwin's resume, awards received, and correspondence. There are also his business files accumulated while city manager. These include minutes of meetings, correspondence, city improvement projects, and surveys. The topical files also contain documents on the MOSES and SEMCOG lawsuit consisting of court documents, clippings, and press, as well as Ferndale's position on the voting structure debate. Project files relates to the Nine Mile streetscape improvement project and the I-75 expansion. The project files also include documents on the "Barwin amendment," which was his effort to amend the Michigan Constitution to increase Detroit Metropolitan area sales taxes by a half-cent in order to fund a rapid transit system.
  - Personal
    - Awards 2001, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1999-2006 (Box 1)
    - Guest speaker for college classes (Box 1)
    - Performance evaluations 2001-2006 (Box 1)
    - Resume (Box 1)
    - Speeches, presentations, talking points (Box 1)
  - City of Ferndale
    - Correspondence 1999-2006 (Box 1)
    - Crow's nest debate 2005 (Box 1)
    - Electrical improvements, Ferndale Parks 1999 (Box 1)
    - EPIC/MRA survey (community and local issues) 1998 (Box 1)
    - Goal setting 2000 (Box 1)
    - Meetings 1999-2004 (Box 1)
    - Residency 1999 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Maps/photos (Box 1)
  - MOSES v. SEMCOG
    - City of Ferndale review of SEMCOG 2003 (Box 1)
    - Clippings and press 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 2004 (Box 1)
    - Court documents 2004 (Box 1)
    - Federal-Aid Urban Boundary (FAUB) map 2000 (Box 1)
    - SEMCOG reform 2004-2006 (Box 1)
  - Organizations
    - Land Use Council report 2003 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Suburbs Alliance 2002-2006 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Transportation Alliance 2003-2005 (Box 1)
    - Projects (Box 1)
    - SEMCOG, Transportation Advisory Council 2004-2005 (Box 1)
  - Projects
    - Barwin amendment 2003-2006 (Box 2)
    - Dollar Castle (Box 2)
    - I-75 expansion (Box 2)
    - Nine Mile road streetscape improvement project 2000 (Box 2)
      (see also outsize folder)
    - Woodward corridor transit alternatives 2000 (Box 2)
  - Reports and writings (Box 2)
  - Transit (Box 2)
  - Wheelchair access (Box 2)
- 8 Mile and Woodward Overpass 2003-2005
  The 8 Mile and Woodward Overpass series (1.5 linear ft., 2003-2005) covers the debate over the 8 Mile and Woodward bridge. Files include correspondence, Michigan Department of Transportation studies and reports, articles and press, as well as the response from citizens and the City of Ferndale on the decision to rebuild the bridge.
  - Project
    - Articles and press 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Consultant selection and contract 2003 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Barwin correspondence, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Sue Datta (MDOT project manager) correspondence, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Data (Box 2)
    - Detroit City Council November 13, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Landscape architectural plan (Box 2)
    - Local Advisory Committee Meeting August 11, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous project materials (Box 2)
    - Project cost 2005 (Box 2)
    - Project documents (Box 2)
    - Transparencies of project documents (Box 2)
  - Response
    - Eight Mile Boulevard Association, Board of Directors meeting July 14, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Feedback on proposal 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Ferndale Chamber of Commerce meetings 2004 (Box 3)
    - Greenacres Woodward Civic Association (opposed to bridge removal) 2003 (Box 3)
    - Information for the public 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous responses (Box 3)
    - Public support for bridge 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Stakeholder survey 2005 (Box 3)
    - Telephone hotline response 2003 (Box 3)
  - Reports and studies
    - Bridge Scoping reports, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Cultural Resources Survey and Literature Search November 2003 (Box 3)
    - Determination of Eligibility for the National Register of Historic Places October 2003 (Box 3)
    - Environmental Assessment
      - Proposal (DMZ Michigan, Inc.) 2003 (Box 3)
      - Work scope 2003 (Box 3)
      - Project kickoff/public meeting September 25, 2003 (Box 3)
      - Community visioning reform December 2003 (Box 3)
      - Photo study 2003 (Box 3)
      - Project updates and correspondence 2003-2004 (Box 3)
      - Second public meeting January 15, 2004 (Box 3)
      - Air quality impact analysis technical report April 2004 (Box 3)
      - Traffic analysis report
        - Appendix D-traffic analysis and performance measures February 2004, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - Appendix E-base year 2003 data, February 2004 (Box 3)
        - April 2004 (revised) (Box 3)
      - Environmental assessment for Mayor Porter (Ferndale) June 7, 2004 (Box 3)
      - Presentation to Detroit City Council June 8, 2004 (Box 3)
      - City of Ferndale and public reaction 2004 (Box 3)
      - Public comment sheet (Box 3)
    - Noise report April 2004 (Box 3)
    - Traffic study August 2001 (Box 3)